you might remember this guy Chung from
注：Secret Informant意思是秘密线人，但是内容都是美食
你还记得上一集里出现过的这位大哥么
our last episode he's the chef and owner
注：中文字幕是官方字幕，未经过修改，而英文字幕和中文字幕的时间轴没对齐，好像还只是自动英文字幕
……看看中文就好了。
这位是香港刘森记面家的老板兼主厨
of Lao some key noodle in Hong Kong as
the name implies this restaurant
注：配音就是techlinked的Riley，还记得他2018年夏天的时候去出差的事吗，就是去香港玩了
店如其名 刘森记面馆的特色
specializes in custom handmade noodles
是香港传统手工面 叫做竹升面
called bamboo noodles they're not made
竹升面是用面粉和鸡蛋做的
from bamboo just eggs and flour
里面并没有竹子
although bamboo is included in the
不过竹竿擀面是竹升面制作的一个重要环节
noodle making process as you'll see in a
等一下马上就能看到
minute that process is once started by
竹升面的制作工艺是从刘森记老板的爷爷创始
Chung's grandfather who taught Chung
一代一代传承至今
father who taught Chung himself the man
今天刘老板不仅仅是在制作手工面
isn't just making noodles is carrying on
更多的是在继承并完善传统家族制作工艺
a family tradition
the mighty noodles start is a humble
传奇竹升面的制作从基础的和面开始
circle of flour which is actually
这些面粉是从加拿大进口的哟
imported from Canada
eggs of both the chicken and duck
在面粉堆得中间敲入鸡蛋和鸭蛋
variety are cracked into the middle and
同时用手进行搅拌
mixed by hand once one batch of eggs is
一批一批的鸡蛋和鸭蛋被接二连三地加入面粉堆中
mixed another is added as the mound of
面粉则渐渐地转型成了可以加工的面团
flour slowly transforms into workable
dough at some point Chong will add a bit
期间刘老板会在面粉团里加入少量碱水
of alkaline water to the mixture if you
碱水加到一定量可以起到防腐效果
add enough it will act as a preservative
allowing you to make large batches of
dough to prepare later on but for the
可以延长面团的新鲜期 供以后使用
不过刘老板每天都会做三到四次面条
daily batches of which Chun makes about
three to four each day just enough is
加入适量碱水能使最后做出来的面条非常有嚼劲
added to give the noodles a slightly
more chewy texture a nice bouncy feel
口感会非常有弹性
soon enough the dough is ready to be
很快面团在容器里被压成了扁平状
shaped into a long flat roll but your
然后就可以开始擀面了
这里用奶奶的擀面杖不够给力了哟
grandma's rolling pin isn't gonna cut it
for this stuff rather here's what that
这里就是请竹竿出场的时候了
bamboo I was talking about earlier comes
in a long cylinder is fit into a special
竹竿的一头会卡在平台另一端事先设置好的铁环里
mount in the wall which Chung will sit
接着刘老板坐在竹竿的另一头
on using his whole body weight to
利用杠杆原理加上自己的体重
compress the dough one section at a time
一点一点将面团压平
making the dough thin enough to move on
反复多次直到面团被压得又扁又长方可开始下一个步骤
to the next step
[Music]
while we watched him toilet imagining
当我们在观察刘老板一步一步做着竹升面
想象着他每天要花几个小时制作的面条
spending hours making something that
hungry diners will devour in seconds I
饥饿的食客则在几秒内就能吃掉一碗面
thought about the fact that Chung is the
我意识到这些面条每天都是刘老板自己一个人做出来的
only guy that makes these noodles and I
我想象刘老板这样年复一年坚持不懈地做着面条
suspect the reason is more a matter of
更多的是对家族遗产的一种尊重与传承
legacy than it is the technicality of
而不是因为做竹升面有很深奥的技术
the task yes he could hire someone else
刘老板大可请人来帮他做面条
to make the noodles for process is made
面条的制作过程每一个制作步骤都很简洁
up of discrete tasks which could
任何人都可以做得到
necessarily be performed by anyone but
不过这种继承先辈传统的使命感
there's something special about walking
the same path the people that brought
并不是每个人都能感受得到的
you into this world the room in which we
在刘老板给我们展示做面过程的房间里
watched Cheung bring these noodles into
being was incredibly hot and literally
非常的热而且到处都盖着一层面粉
covered in flour but to the noodle chef
不过对刘老板来说
it's the place where these noodles have
这是他做了一辈子面条的地方
been made for his entire life he is just
他确实只在这里做面条
making noodles but he's also continuing
不过他在这里继承他祖父和父亲的毕生心血
the work of his father and his father's
father allowing them to live on through
让他们的精神遗产得以长留于世
his labor
[Music]
when the dough reaches the appropriate
当面团被竹竿压得足够扁了之后
thinness it's time to let the machines
这时候机器就要出场了
do the work some of it anyway
不过只是一小部分会用到机器
the dough is put through the first
面团会在第一台机器里面压十次
machine ten times which thins the dough
面团最后会被压成两毫米厚的面皮
out to under two centimeters then he
然后刘老板告诉我们说
tells us he lets the dough rest for
在下一个步骤之前他会让面皮醒十分钟左右
about ten minutes or it might be the
或者是刘老板自己需要歇口气
chef that needs a rest it's only human
他也是凡人嘛
then it's on to Machine number two which
接着就要把醒好的面皮放进第二台机器里面了
这台机器能将刚才粗糙的面皮加一些面粉后压精细
refines the dough and adds a bit more
flour chung tells us that they bought
刘老板告诉我们说他们家在三十年前买的这台机器
this machine 30 years ago before that
在那之前制面的全部步骤都是用竹竿完成的
this whole process was done completely
with bamboo rods which took a much
之前制面花的时间比现在多得多
larger amount of time I guess the bamboo
我想刚才我们看到的竹竿压面
cylinder we saw is the last remnant of
是竹升面整个制作过程中唯一剩下用竹竿的部分了
what used to be an all bamboo process
finally when the dough is essentially
最后当面皮被压成一长条宽面之后
one long flat noodle it's run through a
面皮会通过第三台机器
third machine which shreds it into many
这台机器会将一条大宽面切成细条面
noodles
apparently the batch that we witness
我们目睹的这次面条制作的量
being prepared is enough for a hundred
大约是一百四十碗面
and forty servings of noodles
once those are ready Chung will start in
这一批制作好之后
刘老板就直接开始准备下一批的制作了
the next batch it's interesting to think
我不禁想着这一百四十个吃面条的人
that each of those 140 people may or may
可能并不会非常在乎他们在吃的这些面条
not appreciate the fact that the food
they're eating was carefully and
是由一位继承了祖孙三代竹升面制作工艺精髓的厨师
lovingly handmade by a grandson walking
全心全意手工制作的
in the footsteps of his father's there
香港有很多像刘老板一样的厨师
are so many chefs like Chung
devoting their lives to creating food
倾尽毕身心血为他人做美食
for others some in the spotlight and
他们有一些会在聚光灯下受到关注
others under a regular old light bulb in
也有一些会在一间盖满面粉的普通房间里工作
a flower covered room the crew of secret
Secret Informant 摄制组有幸目睹了这样一个
informant got to see a process that not
没有多少人见过的传统竹升面制作工艺过程
many people do and for that I'm thankful
我们非常感激
and unthankful you for watching this
我们也感谢您观看这一期的视频
video that's it for this one it was a
这一期和往常的内容有些不同
slightly different type of video for us
this series is produced by tattle
Secret Informant 系列视频由 Tattle 制作
witch's a platform connecting savvy
Tattle 是一个帮助探险者连接本地向导的网络平台
locals with curious explorers check them
来我们的社交媒体上看看
out on social media and sign up for the
点击下面的链接订阅 Tattle 的每周电子期刊
newsletter at the link in the
description
big thanks to Laos um key noodle for
再一次感谢刘森记面家协助我们这一集的拍摄
having us again and thanks to Chung for
也感谢刘老板慷慨地为我们展示了他的家传秘方
letting us in on the family secret make
订阅我们的频道看更多视频哟
sure to subscribe to tattle for more
videos like this from secret informant